Finding aid to WAVES (Women Accepted for Voluntary Emergency Services Unit) files CA.MS.00007
Smith College Archives
WAVES files
1939-1996
1942-1945
Smith College Archives
United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve.
CA.MS.00007
2.5 linear feet (10 containers)
Records of the WAVES, Smith College's unit of of the women's Naval Reserve. These files contain books, broadcasts, correspondence, printed materials, press releases, newspaper clippings, memoranda, notes and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
The United States entered WWII in 1941 and soon faced a serious shortage of manpower in the military. Congress, along with public interest and advocacy from various national organizations, forced the Department of the Navy (over considerable internal resistance) to start accepting women into their service to augment the many thousands of men already active in the war effort. On June 24, 1942, Congress passed an act to create a women's reserve as a branch of the Naval reserve; to be governed by the same rules and privileges, but limited in that women could only work non-combat duty in the continental U.S. The idea was to free trained Naval men from desk jobs in order to increase the active fighting force--thus the rallying theme, "Free a man to fight." The new women's Naval Reserve units were called the WAVES (Women Accepted for Voluntary Emergency Services) and, with its sister Coast Guard Reserve the SPARS, proceeded to immediately set up training schools at many colleges and universities across the country. Basic training sites were located in Oklahoma (Oklahoma Agricultural and Mechanical College at Stillwater), Iowa (Iowa State Teacher's College at Cedar Falls), Wisconsin (University of Wisconsin at Madison), Indiana (University of Indiana at Bloomington), and New York state (Hunter College in New York City). Officer training sites were established in Massachusetts at Mt. Holyoke College in South Hadley, and at Smith College in Northampton.
The creation of the WAVES represented a fundamental change that was occurring in American society as the war effort increased. Women were moving from the home into the work force and gaining increasing independence. In WWI, 11,275 women served in the Navy, mainly in secretarial and office positions, but they were not recognized nor was their service publicized, and no formal program existed for their training. In 1942, for the first time women were in uniform, earning the same pay, doing the same work, following the same rules, and receiving the same respect as Navy men. The publicity surrounding the WAVES focused on their independence, intelligence and equality with their male counterparts. However, the naval officers took care to remind everyone of their gender when designing their uniforms. Pants were vetoed in favor of skirts, fitted jackets, and stack heeled shoes that served to emphasize the femininity of the recruits. Women came to the WAVES from all sections of society, bringing a wide variety of skills and experience. Originally, black women were banned from the WAVES, creating a great deal of friction at some of the training schools. The President lifted the ban in 1944 and later that year the first black female officers graduated from the Smith College training school.
By the end of the war over 83,000 women were serving in the Navy, a number significantly over the original estimate of 11,000. They filled positions such as parachute riggers, pharmacist's mates, instrument flying trainers, store keepers, radio dispatchers, clerks, mechanics, lab technicians, mail carriers, decoders, and navigators. Most of the officers were restricted to the rank of lieutenant with the notable exception of Captain Mildred McAfee (the president of Wellesley College) who was the director the WAVES. Soon after peace was declared in 1945, the WAVES and SPARS programs were dismantled and the women who had been in the Navy returned to their homes or civilian jobs.
Scope and Contents
The WAVES files consist of 2.5 linear feet including books, broadcast materials, correspondence, printed materials, press releases, newspaper clippings, memoranda, notes and photographs documenting the Naval training school for women that was located on the Smith College campus from 1942-1945.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. General
II. Publications
III. Photographs
IV. Audio-Visual
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sources unknown
Naval history--Massachusetts--Northampton.; United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve--History--Sources.; Smith College--History--Sources.; United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve.
- Series I: General
  - Alumnae House diary, financial and other records, 1942-45 (Box 180)
  - Alumnae Relations, 1942-43; undated (Box 180)
  - Anniversaries, 1943 (Box 180)
  - Anniversaries, 1944 (Box 180)
  - Benefit Show, Feb. 1944 (Box 180)
  - Board of Directors, 1942-43 (Box 180)
  - Broadcasts: correspondence, 1942-44 (Box 180)
  - Broadcasts by Mr. Davis, 1942-43 (Box 180)
  - Chaplain's Services, 1943 (Box 180)
  - Citations, 1946 (Box 180)
  - Cleaning Women, 1942 (Box 180)
  - Commencements, 1942-44 (Box 180)
  - Commencement Programs, 1942-44 (Box 180)
  - Contract with Navy, 1942-45 (Box 180)
  - Correspondence, 1942-48 (Box 180)
  - Exhibit: Citron, Minna, Dec. 1943 (Box 180)
  - Film "WAVES at Smith College": correspondence, 1943 (Box 180)
    General
    See also Series IV.
  - Financial: Alumnae House Agreement, 1942 (Box 180)
  - Financial: Cleaning Supplies, 1942-43 (Box 180)
  - Financial: Direct Charges, 1942-44 (Box 180)
  - Financial: Direct Charges Paid, 1943-45 (Box 180)
  - Financial: Direct Salaries and Wages, 1944 (Box 180)
  - Financial: Employees at Alumnae House, 1943 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Expense Misc., 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Final Reports, Oct.1943-Dec.1944 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Final Report, Aug.1942-Sept.1943 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: First Proposal to Navy, 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Fuel - Electricity, undated (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Furniture, 1942-44 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Installation Charges, 1942-43 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Lavatory Supplies, 1942-43 (Box 180.1)
  - Financial: Oil, 1942-43 (Box 180.1)
  - History, 1942-80 (Box 180.1)
  - History, 1942-80 (Box 180.1)
  - Housing, 1943 (Box 180.1)
  - Instructions Governing Naval Training School, 1943 (Box 180.1)
  - Keys, undated (Box 180.1)
  - George King, 1942; 1945 (Box 180.1)
  - Letter to Students, 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Helen Lord and Belle Norton, 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Marines, 1944 (Box 180.1)
  - Miss Mason-Schopfer, 1943-44 (Box 180.1)
  - Record of Meetings, 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Mt. Holyoke Naval School, 1943 (Box 180.1)
  - Naval Records, 1945 (Box 180.1)
  - Navy Day, 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Officers: Lt. Com. P. Baker, 1942-43 (Box 180.1)
  - Officers: Lt. Com. Bullis (also office), 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Officers: Crandall, 1942 (Box 180.1)
  - Officers: Lt. Com. M. Disert, 1942-45 (Box 180.1)
  - Officers: Mildred McAfee, 1943-46 (Box 180.2)
  - Officers: Marianne McNees, 1942-44 (Box 180.2)
  - Officers: Lt. Elizabeth Reynard, 1942-45 (Box 180.2)
  - Officers: Lt. Schoonover, 1942-44 (Box 180.2)
    see also Furniture
  - Officers: Capt. Underwood, 1942-44 (Box 180.2)
  - Officers: Louise Wilde, 1942-43 (Box 180.2)
  - Plaque Presentation, Nov. 11, 1947 (Box 180.2)
  - Postals, 1942 (Box 180.2)
  - Procurement, 1942 (Box 180.2)
  - Public Relations, 1942-43 (Box 180.2)
  - Publicity In Smith Alumnae Quarterly, 1942-45 (Box 180.2)
  - Publicity Tour, 1943 (Box 180.2)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1943 (Box 180.2)
  - Schedules, undated (Box 180.2)
  - Florence H. Snow, 1944-45 (Box 180.2)
  - Songs, undated (Box 180.2)
  - Speeches by Mr. Davis, undated (Box 180.2)
  - Smith WAVES members, 1942-45 (Box 180.2)
  - Smith participants, 1942 (Box 180.2)
  - Tea, 1942 (Box 180.2)
  - Tea for Wives, 1942 (Box 180.2)
  - Tea for Smith WAVES, 1942 (Box 180.2)
  - Tea, 1943 (Box 180.2)
  - Tea for Smith WAVES, Feb. 1944 (Box 180.2)
  - WAVES Tea, May 1944 (Box 180.2)
  - Tea for Smith WAVES, Nov. 1944 (Box 180.2)
  - W.A.A.C. - Smith Alumnae, 1945-47 (Box 180.2)
  - [Wanting] Lists, 1942-43 (Box 180.2)
- Series II: Publications
  - General, 1943-44; undated (Box 181)
  - "The Activities of the WAVES, SPARS, and the MCWR at the Naval Reserve (Box 181)
  - Midshipman's School, Northampton, MA", 1943-44 (Box 181)
  - "The Naval Reserve Midshipman's School (Box 181)
  - (WR) Northampton and the Naval Training (Box 181)
  - School (Communications-W) South Hadley, MA", undated (Box 181)
  - Newsletter, 1945-46 (Box 181)
  - "Wave Lengths", 12/4/42-3/11/43 (Box 181)
  - Book - Naval Customs, Traditions and Usage, 1939 (Box 181)
  - Book - Angel of the Navy: The Story Of a WAVE, 1943 (Box 181)
  - Book - The WAVES: The Story of the Girls in Blue by Nancy Wilson Ross [1943] (Box *)
  - Publications - clippings, Jun 1942-Apr 1943 (Box 181.1)
  - Publications - clippings, May 1943- 1996 (Box 181.2)
  - WAVES Clippings, 1946 (Box 181.2)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 181.2)
  - Clippings, 1996 (Box 181.2)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 181.3)
  - General, undated (Box 181.3)
  - Alumnae House Headquarters, undated (Box 181.3)
  - Events, undated (Box 181.3)
  - Marching, undated (Box 181.3)
  - Officers, undated (Box 181.3)
  - Students and Classes, undated (Box 181.3)
  - Publications - Newsletter (Oversize) (Box 8)
    - Sounding Off, vol 1, no. 1-52,vol. 2, no. 1-39, 1943-44 (Box 8)
- Series IV: Audio-Visual
  - Spars and Marines. Coast Guard, W.A., semper paratus?, 1939-45 (Box AV)
  - "Waves at Smith", 1939-45 (Box AV)